# Alireza Farshin | Curriculum Vitae

② aliireza.github.io ● ☑ Alireza Farshin ● ☐ aliireza
in alireza-farshin ● ☑ alirezafarshin

I am a distributed systems researcher at NVIDIA. My research interests include computer networks and networked systems. Before joining NVIDIA, I was a senior researcher I was a senior researcher in the network intelligence unit at RISE. I completed my doctoral studies in the Network Systems Laboratory (NSLab) at KTH Royal Institute of Technology under the supervision of Professor Dejan Kostić and Professor Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. During my doctoral studies, I improved the performance of Network Functions Virtualization (NFV) service chains by using low-level optimization techniques.

# **Work Experience**

Networking Software Architecture Research Team at NVIDIA

Connected Intelligence Unit at RISE Research Institutes of Sweden

Stockholm, Sweden
January 2024–now

Distributed Systems Researcher

Stockholm, Sweden

Senior Researcher in AI / Machine Learning and Networking

August 2023–January 2024

- Improving packet processing at multi-100-Gbps rates.
- Using large language models (LLMs) to build and configure networked systems (see NetBuddy).
- Developing pruning techniques and improving inference of LLMs.

Network Systems Laboratory (NSLab) at KTH

Postdoctoral Researcher

Stockholm, Sweden March 2023–August 2023

Network Systems Laboratory (NSLab) at KTH

Doctoral Researcher

Stockholm, Sweden August 2017–March 2023

ICT Doctoral Programme Council at KTH

Student Representative of the Division of Communication Systems (CoS)

**Stockholm, Sweden** *May 2018–December 2020* 

Mobile Telecommunication Company of Iran (MCCI)

Portal Specialist

**Tehran, Iran** *December 2015–June 2016* 

Vendor Manager & Portal/Application Supervisor:

- eCare Application: My MCI Application for iOS and Android
- eSales Website: eVoucher

CafeYab Tehran, Iran

Co-founder and CEO

Fall-2013

An application for iOS and Android for finding nearby Coffee Shops

Informatics Services Corporation (ISC)

Tehran, Iran

Internship

June 2013-September 2013

- Ported an RF unit controller from PIC-16F877A to AtMega64A and tested the new module.
- Designed a remote-control system with HM-T and HM-R FSK modules.

### **Publications**

#### Conference Publications.....

[C1] Hamid Ghasemirahni, Tom Barbette, Georgios Katsikas, Alireza Farshin, Massimo Girondi, Amir Roozbeh, Marco Chiesa, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Packet Order Matters! Improving Application Performance by Deliberately Delaying Packets In 19th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI). 2022. Acceptance rate (Spring): 28/104 ≈ 26.9%, (conference rank A). [Community Award Winner!] Download

- [C2] Alireza Farshin, Tom Barbette, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. <u>PacketMill</u>: Toward per-core 100-Gbps Networking In *International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)*. 2021. Acceptance rate: 75/398 ≈ 18.8%, (conference rank A\*). Download
- [C3] Alireza Farshin, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Reexamining Direct Cache Access to Optimize I/O Intensive Applications for Multi-hundred-gigabit Networks In *USENIX Annual Technical Conference (ATC)*. 2020. Acceptance rate: 65/348 ≈ 18.6%, (conference rank A). <u>Download</u>
- [C4] Alireza Farshin, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Make the Most out of Last Level Cache in Intel Processors In *The European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys)*. 2019. Acceptance rate: 45/207 ≈ 21.7%, (conference rank A). <u>Download</u>

## Journal Publications.....

- [J1] Alireza Farshin, Luigi Rizzo, Khaled Elmeleegy, Dejan Kostić. Overcoming the IOTLB wall for multi-100-Gbps Linux-based networking In *PeerJ Computer Science* (*PeerJ CS*). 2023. Impact factor: 2.41. <a href="Download">Download</a>
- [J2] Alireza Farshin, Saeed Sharifian. A modified knowledge-based ant colony algorithm for virtual machine placement and simultaneous routing of NFV in distributed cloud architecture In *The Journal of Supercomputing (SUPE)*. 2019. Impact factor: 2.469. Download
- [J3] Alireza Farshin, Saeed Sharifian. A chaotic grey wolf controller allocator for Software Defined Mobile Network (SDMN) for 5th generation of cloud-based cellular systems (5G) In *The Journal of Computer Communications* (COMCOM). 2017. Impact factor: 2.816. Download
- [J4] Alireza Farshin, Saeed Sharifian. MAP-SDN: a metaheuristic assignment and provisioning SDN framework for cloud datacenters In *The Journal of Supercomputing (SUPE)*. 2017. Impact factor: 2.469. <a href="Download">Download</a>

### Patent Applications....

- [P1] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Marco Chiesa. Entity and Method Performed Therein for Handling Packets in a Computer Environment (*Other name:* System and Methods for Performing Millions Low-Latency Key-Value Insertion on Switches). PCT Application PCT/SE2023/051174. Filed in November 2023.
- [P2] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Marco Chiesa, Dejan Kostić. Network Entity and Method Performed Therein for Handling one or more Packets in a Computer Environment (Other name: System and Methods for Minimizing Branch Mispredictions and Executing Highly Optimized Code for Networking Applications). PCT Application PCT/SE2023/050880. Filed in September 2023.
- [P3] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Marco Chiesa. Network Entity and Method Performed Therein for Handling one or more Packets in a Computer Environment (Other name: System and Methods for Programmatically Storing Packet Payloads in the Per-Port Queue Memory). US Provisional Patent Application 63/511,198. Filed in June 2023.
- [P4] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Marco Chiesa. System and Method Performed Therein for Handling one or more Packets in a Computer Environment (Other name: System and Methods for Disaggregated Packet Construction). PCT Application PCT/SE2023/050538. Filed in May 2023.
- [P5] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Marco Chiesa, Dejan Kostić, Hamid Ghasemirahni. Hint Entity, Receiver Node, System and Methods Performed Therein for Handling Data in a Computer Environment (Other name: System and Methods for Network-Accelerated State Prefetching). PCT Application PCT/SE2022/051036. Filed in November 2022.
- [P6] Amir Roozbeh, Chakri Padala, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Processing Unit, Packet Handling Unit, Arrangement and Methods for Handling Packets (*Other name:* System and Methods

- for Probing and Polling Multiple I/O Operations on I/O Devcies for Priority-Based Packet Processing). PCT Application PCT/SE2022/050710. Download
- [P7] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Marco Chiesa, Tom Barbette, Dejan Kostić. Packet Processing Including an Ingress Packet Part Distributor. PCT Application PCT/EP2023/063619. <a href="Download">Download</a>
- [P8] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić. System and Method for Organizing Physical Queues into Virtual Queues. PCT Application PCT/EP2022/051103. <u>Download</u>
- [P9] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Marco Chiesa, Fabio Luciano Verdi. System and Method for Accurate Traffic Monitoring on Multi-Pipeline Switches. PCT Application PCT/EP2021/084572. <u>Download</u>
- [P10] Amir Roozbeh, Chakri Padala, **Alireza Farshin**. System and Method for Cache pooling and Efficient Usage and I/O Transfer in disaggregated and Multi-Processor Architectures via Processor Interconnect. PCT Application PCT/SE2021/051016. <u>Download</u>
- [P11] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Chakri Padala, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. System, Method, and Apparatus for Fine-grained Control of I/O Data Placement in Memory Subsystem. PCT Application PCT/SE2021/050803. <u>Download</u>
- [P12] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Tom Barbette, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Methods and Systems for Efficient Metadata and Data Delivery between a Network Interface and Applications. PCT Application PCT/IB2021/052976. <u>Download</u>
- [P13] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Method and System for Efficient Input/Output Transfer in Network Devices. PCT Application PCT/SE2020/051107 (<u>Download</u>) & PCT/SE2020/051108 (<u>Download</u>).
- [P14] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr, Hamid Ghasemirahni, Tom Barbette. Reordering and Reframing Packets. PCT Application PCT/IB2020/054991. <u>Download</u>
- [P15] Chakri Padala, Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Efficient Loading of Code Portions to a Cache. PCT Application PCT/SE2020/050527. <u>Download</u>
- [P16] Amir Roozbeh, Alireza Farshin, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Entities, System and Methods Performed Therein for Handling Memory Operations of an Application in a Computer Environment. PCT Application PCT/SE2019/050948. <u>Download</u>
- [P17] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Methods and Devices for Controlling Memory Handling. PCT Application PCT/SE2020/050161. <u>Download</u>
- [P18] Amir Roozbeh, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., **Alireza Farshin**. Memory Allocation in a Hierarchical Memory System. PCT Application PCT/SE2019/050596. <u>Download</u>
- [P19] Amir Roozbeh, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr. Methods and Nodes for Handling Memory. PCT Application PCT/SE2018/051311. <u>Download</u> ( <u>US11714753B2 Granted</u>)

### Workshop Papers, Extended Abstracts, Preprints, Technical Reports, Demo, and Posters....

- [W1] Hamid Ghasemirahni, Alireza Farshin, Mariano Scazzariello, Marco Chiesa, Dejan Kostić. Deploying Stateful Network Functions Efficiently using Large Language Models In *The Workshop on Machine Learning* and Systems (EuroMLSys). 2024. <u>Download</u>
- [W2] Changjie Wang, Mariano Scazzariello, **Alireza Farshin**, Dejan Kostić, Marco Chiesa. Making Network Configuration Human Friendly, *ArXiv Preprint*. 2023. <u>Download</u>
- [W3] Alireza Farshin, Amir Roozbeh, Christian Schulte, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Scheduling A Secret Sauce For Resource Disaggregation, *Technical Report*. 2021. Download

- [W4] Alireza Farshin, Tom Barbette, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. <a href="PacketMill: Toward">PacketMill: Toward</a> per-core 100-Gbps Networking In International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS). 2021. <a href="Download">Download</a>
- [W5] Alireza Farshin, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Optimizing Intel Data Direct I/O Technology for Multi-hundred-gigabit Networks In *The European Conference on Computer Systems* (*EuroSys*). 2020. <u>Download</u>
- [W6] Alireza Farshin, Amir Roozbeh, Gerald Q. Maguire Jr., Dejan Kostić. Make the Most out of Last Level Cache in Intel Processors In *The European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys)*. 2019. Download

# **Funded Projects**

### **SEMLA** - Securing Enterprises via Machine-Learning-based Automation

~9.5 Million SEK

Funded by Vinnova - Cyber Security for Industrial Advanced Digitalization 2023

Acted as one of the co-Pls from RISE AB

other partners: KTH (led by Marco Chiesa), Saab AB, and RedHat AB

Realizing Low-Latency Internet Services via Low-Level Optimization of NFV Service Chains

\$140,000 USD

August 2021–August 2023

Funded by Google PhD Fellowship in Systems and Networking

# **Open-Source Contributions**

[7	iommu-bench: Understanding the IOTLB Wall for Multi-100-Gbps Linux-based Networking [Link]
	DDC-RA: A Constrained-based Scheduler for Disaggregated Data Centers (DDC) [Link]
	PacketMill: Toward per-core 100-Gbps Networking [Link]
	ddio-bench: Understanding Intel Data Direct I/O Technology [Link]
	Slice-aware Memory Management: Exploiting NUCA Characteristic of LLC in Intel Processors [Link]
$\Box$	CacheDirector: Sending Packets to the Right Slice by Exploiting Intel Last-Level Cache Addressing [Link]

### **Education**

### KTH Royal Institute of Technology

Stockholm, Sweden

Ph.D. in Information and Communication Technology, School of EECS Advisors: Prof. Dejan Kostić and Prof. Gerald Q. Maguire Jr.

August 2017–March 2023

Dissertation Title: Realizing Low-Latency Packet Processing on Multi-Hundred-Gigabit-Per-Second Commodity Hardware (see my <u>Dissertation</u>)

I also received my <u>licentiate</u> degree (Halfway to Ph.D.) in June 2019, see my <u>Thesis</u>.

### Amirkabir University of Technology

Tehran, Iran

M.Sc. Electrical Engineering - Digital Electronic Circuits, Department of EE September 2015—July 2017
Advisor: Associate Prof. Saeed Sharifian

Thesis: Resource Allocation in Software-Defined Networks for 5G Applications I used bio-inspired metaheuristic algorithms to perform resource allocation.

#### **Sharif University of Technology**

Tehran, Iran

B.Sc. Electrical Engineering - Electronics, EE Department Advisor: Associate Prof. Mehran Jahed

September 2010-July 2015

Thesis: Design of Exoskeletal System for Wrist and Forearm

## Honors, Awards, and Professional Services

- 2023: Faculty at Digital Futures.
- 2023: Reviewer for IEEE Computer Architecture Letters.
- 2022: Packet Order Matters! [C1] was featured in the Ericsson Blog and KTH.
- 2022: "Framtidens Forskning" has published a <a href="Swedish article">Swedish article</a> on my research.
- 2022: PC Member for SIGCOMM'22 posters and demos program.
- 2022: Packet Order Matters! [C1] received the "Community Award" at NSDI'22.
- 2022: Giving a talk, Optimization Techniques for NFV, at Cisco Engineering Switzerland.
- 2021: Awarded Google PhD Fellowship 2021 in Systems and Networking. [Interview with KTH EECS]
- 2021: PacketMill [C2] was featured in the Ericsson Blog.
- 2021: Giving a talk with Tom Barbette at FOSDEM'21. [Watch]
- 2020: EuroSys'20 Shadow Program Committee.
- 2019: CacheDirector [C4] was featured in the Ericsson Blog, Tech Xplore, AlphaGalileo, and KTH.
- 2018: External Reviewer for NSDI'19.
- 2015: Ranked 107th among more than 20,000 participants in Iran's universities entrance exam for M.Sc.
- 2010: Ranked 46<sup>th</sup> among more than 460,000 participants in Iran's universities entrance exam for B.Sc.

# **Teaching Experience**

Communication System Design (<u>IK2200</u>), KTH. Fall 2022,2021,2020,2019,2018,2017.

SDN and NFV (<u>IK2220</u>), KTH. Spring 2022,2021,2020,2019.

Bio-Inspired Artificial Intelligence, Amirkabir University of Technology. Fall 2016.

### Skills

Languages: English (Fluent), Persian (Native), Swedish (Novice)

Programming Languages: C/C++, Python, MATLAB, Scala, R, Assembly-X86, bash.

Tools & Libraries: DPDK, FastClick, Perf, LLVM, TensorFlow, Pandas, Spark, Gecode, Git, gnuplot, LATEX.

### **Hobbies**

Playing Piano and Bass Guitar, Jamming with Friends, Reading Books, Watching Movies and TV Series.